Finding aid to Office of the President Marion Le Roy Burton files CA.MS.00009
Smith College Archives
Office of the President Marion Le Roy Burton files
1874-1941
Smith College Archives
Burton, Marion Le Roy, 1874-1925.
CA.MS.00009
4.792 linear feet (12 containers)
Marion LeRoy Burton was the second president of Smith College and later president of the University of Minnesota and the University of Michigan. This collection contains correspondence, publications, sermons, photographs, and press articles.
Biographical / Historical
Marion Le Roy Burton, the second president of Smith College, was born in Brooklyn, Iowa on 30 August 1874, the youngest child of Ira and Jane Simmons Burton. The family moved to Minneapolis when Burton was very young. A short time later Ira Burton died after suffering financial reverses. Jane Burton worked hard to support her family and her sons took jobs after school to ease the financial strain. Burton's early jobs included selling newspapers and raising pigeons.
The day after his 1900 graduation from Carlton College, Burton married classmate Nina L. Moses, and they went to Minnesota's Windom Institute to gain teaching experience. By this time, he had decided that a college presidency was the job for him and would let nothing draw him from that path. With this goal in mind and the knowledge that all college presidents of the day were clergymen, Burton went to Yale University to study theology and earn his Ph.D. in philosophy. He graduated summa cum laude in. Leaving Yale in 1908, having taught there after his graduation, Burton went to preach at the historic Church of the Pilgrims in Brooklyn, New York. The following year, Smith offered him the presidency and he was inaugurated in 1910.
The institution Burton came to lead in 1910 was in a precarious position. Though the original endowment had been shrewdly managed and substantially enlarged, it was not enough to provide for the vast improvements the College needed. These included a new gymnasium, two laboratories, more student housing and a larger campus. To pay for these improvements, Burton announced a million-dollar fundraising campaign. Such an ambitious campaign had not been embarked on before and, despite the doubts of many, it succeeded. During his seven years at Smith, Burton encouraged changes in the curriculum designed to meet more of the challenges students would be facing in the outside world and significantly altered the admissions procedure to a more comprehensive examination of the student's abilities, achievements, interests and character. One of Burton's greatest dreams for Smith was a vast enlargement of the campus to provide for semi-separate schools devoted to different areas of study, resulting in Smith College changing into Sophia Smith University. The plan was received relatively well and plans were made to acquire the necessary land, but Burton left Smith before much could be accomplished and without his energy behind the project, it fell through.
In 1917, Burton resigned from Smith, to the despair of the entire college community, to become president of the University of Minnesota. His time at the University of Minnesota was very brief, only three years, but he is credited with keeping the students' morale up during the difficult war years. In 1920, Burton accepted the presidency of the University of Michigan and threw himself into the school's campaign for more and much-needed buildings and brought greater organization to the large and complicated university. He died suddenly from pneumonia on 18 February 1925.
Burton was mourned deeply at the schools he had headed. Following his death, the Smith College Alumnae Association, noting his interest in the cause of students of limited means, began raising money for a scholarship in his name devoted to that cause.
Scope and Contents
The bulk of the Office of the President Marion LeRoy Burton files contain his correspondence between 1909-1917, leading up to and during his years as Smith College president. Other materials include publications, sermons, photographs and press articles.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into five series:
I. Correspondence
II. Biography
III. Smith Documents
IV. Inauguration
V. Publications
Conditions Governing Access
The papers are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Marion Le Roy Burton Office of the President files were donated over a period of time to the Smith College archives from a variety of sources.
Smith College -- presidents; Burton, Marion Le Roy, 1874-1925.; Smith College--Presidents.; Seelye, Laurenus Clark, 1837-1924.; Comstock, Ada Louise.; Smith College. Office of President.
- Series I. Correspondence, 1909-1917; 3.43 linear feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series, the largest in the collection, is organized alphabetically, with various categories breaking down into subcategories (i.e. Academic Departments: Astronomy, Art, Biblical Literature, etc; Board of Trustees: Baldwin, Clark, Comstock, etc.). The only organizational irregularity is Burton's "Outgoing Correspondence" which is located at the front of Box # 304. This series is largely made up of letters to and from members of the Board of Trustees, faculty, Alumnae and students. The folders are all clearly labeled and dated where information is available.
  - Outgoing correspondence note book, 1915-16 (Box 304)
  - A, 1911-16 (Box 304)
  - Academic Departments
    - Art, 1913-17; undated (Box 304)
    - Astronomy, 1911-16; undated (Box 304)
    - Biblical Literature and Comparative (Box 304)
    - Religion, 1913-17; undated (Box 304)
    - Botany, 1913-16 (Box 304)
    - Chemistry, 1912-17 (Box 304)
    - Economics and Sociology, 1910-17; undated (Box 304)
    - Education, 1914 (Box 304)
    - Elocution, 1911-17; undated (Box 304)
    - English Language and Literature, 1910-17; undated (Box 304)
    - French Language and Literature, 1911-17; undated (Box 304)
    - Geology, 1914-17; undated (Box 304)
    - Germanic Languages and Literatures, 1911-15; undated (Box 304)
    - Greek Language and Literature, 1912 (Box 304)
    - History, 1912-17 (Box 304)
    - Italian, 1913; undated (Box 304)
    - Latin Language and Literature, 1911-17 (Box 304)
    - Mathematics, 1916 (Box 304)
    - Museum, 1910-17 (Box 304)
    - Music, 1910-17; undated (Box 304)
    - Philosophy and Psychology, 1914-16 (Box 304)
    - Physical Education, 1911-17; undated (Box 304)
    - Physics, 1910-17; undated (Box 304)
    - Spanish, 1915-17; undated (Box 304)
    - Zoology, 1910-17; undated (Box 304)
  - Alumnae Association, 1909-17; undated (Box 305)
  - Alumnae Correspondence, 1910-16; undated (Box 305)
  - American College for Girls at Constantinople, 1911-12 (Box 305)
  - American School of Classical Study, 1913 (Box 305)
  - Archives, 1917 (Box 305)
  - Association of Collegiate Alumnae, 1912-13 (Box 305)
  - B, 1911-17 (Box 305)
  - Bassett, John Spencer, 1912-16 (Box 305)
  - Beckwith, Martha Warren, 1915-17 (Box 305)
  - Benedict, Suzan Rose, 1914; 1917 (Box 305)
  - Botanic Garden, 1911-17; undated (Box 305)
  - Brimmer School, 1913; 1915 (Box 305)
  - Brown, Charles R., 1916-17 (Box 305)
  - Bryn Mawr College, 1911-15 (Box 305)
  - Buildings, Superintendent of, 1911-1917 (Box 305)
    - General Insurance, 1916-17 (Box 305)
    - James I. Wingate and Co., 1912-14; undated (Box 305)
  - C, 1912-17 (Box 305)
  - Carman, Esther E., 1911-16; undated (Box 305)
  - Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching, 1910-17 (Box 305)
  - Chapin, F. Stuart, 1912-17 (Box 305)
  - Cheever, Louisa Sewall, 1914-17 (Box 305)
  - Churchill, Alfred Vance, 1914-17. undated (Box 305)
  - [Class of 1904 Decennial Gift Committee, 1913-14]----Missing (Box 305)
  - Cobb, Harriet Redfield, 1914-16; undated (Box 305)
  - Cobb, Mary S., 1911; 1916; undated (Box 305)
  - Committees
    - on Advanced Standing, undated (Box 305)
    - Board of Admission, 1915-17 (Box 305)
    - Board of Faculty Advisers, 1916-17 (Box 305)
    - on College Preparatory Schools, 1915 (Box 305)
    - on the Course of Study, 1916? (Box 305)
    - on Dishonest Work, 1916 (Box 305)
    - Examining Board, 1912 (Box 305)
    - on Freshman Honors, 1917 (Box 305)
    - [on Funds for Attendance at Meetings of Learned Societies], 1917 (Box 305)
    - on Graduate Instruction, 1911-17; undated (Box 305)
    - on Honors, 1917; undated (Box 305)
    - on the Inauguration of Marion Le Roy Burton, 1910-11; undated (Box 305)
    - on the President's Reception at Commencement, 1915-17 (Box 305)
    - on Reception of Students, 1912-16 (Box 305)
    - on Recommendations, 1917 (Box 305)
    - on Research, 1917 (Box 305)
    - on Revision of the Curriculum, 1913-16; undated (Box 305)
    - on Schedule, 1915-17; undated (Box 305)
    - on the Shakespeare Prize, 1912; undated (Box 305)
  - Curtis, Mary Beach, 1915-17 (Box 306)
  - Cutler, Anna Alice, 1910; 1912; 1915 (Box 306)
  - D, 1911-17 (Box 306)
  - Dean, Office of, 1912-17; undated (Box 306)
  - Deane, Sidney Norton, 1912-17; undated (Box 306)
  - Delpit, Louise, 1913-16; undated (Box 306)
  - Duckett, Eleanor Shipley, 1916 (Box 306)
  - Dunn, Emmett Reid, 1916-17 (Box 306)
  - E, 1912-17 (Box 306)
  - Egan, Rose F., 1915-16 (Box 306)
  - Eisenbrey, Clara M., 1911-12 (Box 306)
  - Emerick, Charles, 1914-16 (Box 306)
  - F, 1910-16 (Box 306)
  - Faculty, Secretary of, 1910-17 (Box 306)
  - Fay, Sidney Bradshaw, 1914-17 (Box 306)
  - Filer, Grace, 1914-15 (Box 306)
  - Foster, Mary Louise, 1912-17; undated (Box 306)
  - Freeman, Ethel Hale, 1912-17 (Box 306)
  - Fuller, Mary Breese, 1912-17; undated (Box 306)
  - G, 1911-17 (Box 306)
  - Gamble Foundation, 1916-17 (Box 306)
  - Ganong, William Francis, 1915-17; undated (Box 306)
  - Gardiner, Harry Norman, 1910-17 (Box 306)
  - Gates, Charles G. and Florence H. and estate, 1913 (Box 306)
  - Gates Foundation, 1914; 1916 (Box 306)
  - General Education Board, 1911-1915 (Box 306)
    - --Rockefeller Fund (Box 306)
  - Gill, Laura Drake, 1913-15 (Box 306)
    General
    see also Trustees
  - Gragg, Florence Alden, 1910-17 (Box 306)
  - Grant, Elihu, 1913-17 (Box 306)
  - Gray, William Dodge, 1910-17 (Box 306)
  - H, 1912-17 (Box 306)
  - Hampshire Bookshop, 1916-17 (Box 306)
  - Hanscom, Elizabeth Deering, 1912-17 (Box 306)
  - Harvard/Princeton Universities, 1914-15 (Box 306)
  - Hazen, Charles Downer, 1912-17 (Box 306)
  - Hildt, John Coffey, 1914-17 (Box 306)
  - Hobart College, 1913-14 (Box 306)
  - Holzworth, Charles, 1911-14 (Box 306)
  - Honorary Degrees, 1914; 1916 (Box 306)
  - Hopkins, Mary Murray, 1914-1 (Box 306)
  - Houses/Heads of Houses, 1912; 1914; undated (Box 306)
  - Hunt, Agnes, 1912-15; undated (Box 306)
  - I, 1911 (Box 306)
  - Infantile Paralysis, 1916 (Box 306)
  - Intercollegiate Bureau of Occupations, 1911-12 (Box 306)
  - J, 1912-17 (Box 307)
  - J.B. Pond Lyceum Bureau, 1915 (Box 307)
  - J.P. Morgan & Co., 1915; undated (Box 307)
  - Jordan, Mary Augusta, 1912-16; undated (Box 307)
  - K, 1910-17 (Box 307)
  - Kapp, Marie F., 1911-12 (Box 307)
  - King, Helen Maxwell, 1913-17; undated (Box 307)
  - L, 1910-17 (Box 307)
  - Lanning, William H., 1910-15 (Box 307)
  - LeDuc, Alma, 1911-16; undated (Box 307)
  - Lee, Carrie Case, 1912-16; undated (Box 307)
  - Lee, Jennette, 1910-15; undated (Box 307)
  - Library, 1910-17; undated (Box 307)
  - Linehan, Mary L., 1916-17 (Box 307)
  - Locke, Arthur Ware, 1915 (Box 307)
  - M, 1911-17 (Box 307)
  - Marshall, undated (Box 307)
  - McCracken, Henry Noble, 1913-15; undated (Box 307)
  - Michaud, Jennie Chase, 1914-16 (Box 307)
  - Michaud, Regis, 1913-17 (Box 307)
  - Miller, Barnette, 1915-17 (Box 307)
  - Miller, William J., 1914-17 (Box 307)
  - Montgomery, Cornelia A., 1916 (Box 307)
  - N, 1911-16 (Box 307)
  - Newell, Anna Grace, 1913-16 (Box 307)
  - Newell, Jane I., 1915-16; undated (Box 307)
  - Nolen, John: correspondence and report, 1913-16 (Box 307)
  - Northampton, 1913-16; undated (Box 307)
  - O, 1911-17 (Box 308)
  - P, 1911-17 (Box 308)
  - Page, Frederick H., 1915 (Box 308)
  - Panama-Pacific International Exposition, 1914-15; undated (Box 308)
  - Parker, Clara M.W. (Mrs. C.E.), 1911-15; undated (Box 308)
  - Peace Mission, undated (Box 308)
  - Physician, Office of, 1912-17; undated (Box 308)
  - Pigeon, Anne Gardner, 1911-13 (Box 308)
  - Pinkerton's National Detective Agency, 1915 Apr-Jun (Box 308)
  - Powell, Lyman P., 1910-14; undated (Box 308)
  - Prenez, Blanche, 1915-17 (Box 308)
  - Presbyterian Ministers' Fund, 1915 (Box 308)
  - President, Office of, 1916 (Box 308)
  - Psychological Bulletin, 1913-14 (Box 308)
  - Q, 1915 (Box 308)
  - R, 1910-16 (Box 308)
  - [Rally Day, 1914-15] (Box 308)
    ---Missing
  - Registrar, Office of, 1911-17 (Box 308)
  - Rice, Richard Ashley, Jr., 1915-16; undated (Box 308)
  - Richardson, Mary Lilias, 1910-15 (Box 308)
  - Rosseter, Louise W., 1912-16; undated (Box 308)
  - S, 1910-17 (Box 308)
  - Schinz, Albert, 1913-17; undated (Box 308)
  - Scott, Mary Augusta, 1911-17 (Box 308)
  - Scott, Walter, 1912-13 (Box 308)
  - Seelye, Laurenus Clark, 1909-15 (Box 308)
  - Shields, Emily Ledyard, 1915 (Box 308)
  - Smith College Association for Christian Work (SCACW), 1911-13 (Box 308)
  - Sophia Smith University, 1916 (Box 308)
  - Southern Association of College Women, 1910-12; undated (Box 308)
  - Spalding, Martha Reed, 1911; undated (Box 309)
  - Sperry, Pauline, 1911-16
  - Stetson-Fuller, Louise, 1913-16
  - T, 1910-17
  - Taft, William Howard, 1914
  - Townsend, H.G., 1914
  - Treasurer, Office of, 1909-17; undated
  - Trustees, Board of
    - General, 1913-14; undated
    - Baldwin, Ruth Standish, 1913-17
    - Clark, John B., 1912-17
    - Comstock, Ada Louise, 1911-12
    - Davies, Thomas F., 1915-17; undated
    - Dill, James B., 1910
    - Emerson, Ellen Tucker, 1916
    - Gallagher, H. Clifford, 1911-17
    - Gill, Laura Drake, 1909-10
      (see also general)
    - Gillett, Arthur L., 1910-17
    - Greene, John Morton, 1909-17
    - Lamont, Thomas William, 1911-17; undated
    - McCall, Samuel W., 1912-17 (Box 310)
    - Noyes, Lucia Clapp, 1909-14; undated (Box 310)
    - Roberts, Charles A., 1911-17; undated (Box 310)
    - [Wells, Marguerite Milton, 1914-17; undated]--Missing (Box 310)
    - Willard, Elisa May, 1912-15 (Box 310)
    - Williston, A. Lyman, 1909-15; undated (Box 310)
  - Tryon, Dwight William, 1911-14 (Box 310)
  - Turner, Julia E., 1912-14 (Box 310)
  - Tyler, Henry Mather, 1910-12. undated (Box 310)
  - Underwood, George A., 1914-17 (Box 310)
  - V, 1910-17 (Box 310)
  - Van Kleeck, Mary, 1912; 1915 (Box 310)
  - Vassar College, 1915-16 (Box 310)
  - Vincens, Berthe, 1912-13 (Box 310)
  - W - Z, 1911-17 (Box 310)
  - Waterman, Frank Allan, 1914-17 (Box 310)
  - Wilder, Harris Hawthorne, 1911-16 (Box 310)
- Series II. Biography, 1874-1941; .49 linear feet
  The biographical series includes information on Burton's family history (including an incomplete genealogy compiled by his brother), his time at Carleton College, Yale University, the Church of the Pilgrims, Smith College and the Universities of Minnesota and Michigan, as well as various obituaries and memorial pamphlets. Also included are a few sources (mainly newspaper articles) relating to several members of the Burton family. Most of the photographs are of Burton himself, including many studio portraits. There are also many of his inauguration, some of his family life (mainly with Mrs. Burton) and a few candid shots taken at various times. The photographs are arranged by subject.
  - Photographs
    - Portraits, 1913-1917 (Box 311)
    - President and Mrs. Burton, 1911-1914
    - Sillouettes, by Alfred Vance Churchill, undated
    - Portrait, Class of 1891, 1917
    - Portraits, formal, 1910-1911
    - Family, 1910
  - Biographical Materials
    - University of Michigan, 1919-1920; undated
    - University of Minnesota, 1917-1919
    - Personal Correspondence, 1910-1920
    - Phi Beta Kappa Honor Society, 1914-1915
  - Presidency of Smith College, 1909
    - Baccalaureate Address, "The Meaning of America", undated
    - General
    - Memorials, 1925-1927
    - Obituatries, 1925
- Series III. Smith College Documents, 1910-1917; .49 linear feet
  This series contains various documents relating to Burton's seven-year tenure at Smith College. These documents include information about conferences he attended while president, newspaper and magazine articles from those years, plans for the building of the Quadrangle and information about his resignation in 1917.
  - Conference of Women's College Presidents, 1916May (Box 311)
  - Funds
    - Million Dollar Fund, 1911-1912 (Box 312)
    - Gift Book, 1911-1913 (Box 312)
  - Press Information, 1914 (Box 312)
  - Quadrangle Plans, 1914 (Box 312)
  - Receptions, 1915 (Box 312)
  - Resignation, 1917 (Box 312)
  - Speeches, announcements, 1906-1917 (Box 312)
    - Memorial Service for Ludmilla Peck, 1913Apr 13 (Box 312)
- Series IV. Inauguration, 1910; .49 linear feet
  This series is devoted to materials relating to Burton's inauguration as the second president of Smith College. These materials includes copies of Burton's inaugural speech, various other speeches made that day, a program of events of the Burton Inauguration, copies and lists of invitations, newspaper and magazine articles relating to the event and photographs of the event.
  - Publication, "The Inauguration of President Burton, 1910 (Box 313)
  - Addresses, 1910 (Box 313)
  - Committee on Inaugural Proceedings, 1910 (Box 313)
  - Correspondence, 1910 (Box 313)
  - Invitation lists, 1910 (Box 313)
  - News Releases, 1910 (Box 313)
  - Official Documents, 1910 (Box 313)
  - Order of Exercises, 1910 (Box 313)
  - Photographs, 1910 (Box 313)
- Series V. Publications, 1910-1925; .49 linear feet
  The Publications series contains copies of many of Burton's publications, both books and articles, on various topics ranging from the curriculum of Smith College to thoughts on his own Christian faith.
  - The Secret of Achievement: Baccalaureate Address, 1913 (Box 314)
  - The Life Which Is Life Indeed: Baccalaureate Address, 1914 (Box 314)
  - First Things: Baccalaureate Address, 1915 (Box 314)
  - On Being Divine: Baccalaureate Address, 1916 (Box 314)
    (all published by The Pilgrim Press, Boston & Chicago)
  - Old Man Dare's Talks to College Men, Introduction by Marion L. Burton (NY:Fleming H. Revell Co.), 1922 (Box 314)
  - Our Intellectual Attitude in An Age of Criticism (Boston&Chicago: The Pilgrim Press), 1913 (Box 314)
  - The Problem of Evil: A Criticism of the Augustinian Point of View (Chicago:Open Court Publishing Co.), 1909 (Box 314)
  - Articles
    - Various, fragments, undated (Box 314)
    - "The Age-Long Lesson" Good Housekeeping, 1918Dec (Box 314)
    - From The Smith Alumnae Quarterly:
      - The New Curriculum, 1915Nov (Box 314)
      - The Present Status of the Million Dollar Campaign, 1912Apr (Box 314)
      - To The Alumna, 1911Jan (Box 314)
      - Being Divine, 1916Jul (Box 314)
      - The New Method of Admission, 1916Apr (Box 314)
      - "That Mind of Yours," Kiwanis Magazine, 1925Feb (Box 314)
      - "Why Am I A Christian?" North American Student, undated (Box 314)
  - Books
    - Newbury Brookfield, 1907 (Box 315)